<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-opswg-mud-tls-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MUD TLS profile for IoT devices">MUD (D)TLS profiles for
    IoT devices</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Citrix">Citrix Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4988 Great America Pkwy</street>

          <city>Santa Clara</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95054</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>danwing@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>OPSWG WG</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo extends Manufacturer Usage Description (MUD) to model DTLS
      and TLS usage. This allows a network element to notice abnormal DTLS or
      TLS usage which has been strong indicator of other software running on
      the endpoint, typically malware.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Encryption is necessary to protect the privacy of end users using IoT
      devices. In a network setting, TLS <xref target="RFC8446"></xref> and
      DTLS <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-dtls13"></xref> are the dominant
      protocols to provide encryption for IoT device traffic. Unfortunately in
      conjunction with IoT applications rise of encryption, malware is also
      using encryption which thwarts network-based analysis such as deep
      packet inspection (DPI). Other mechanisms are needed to notice malware
      is running on the IoT device.</t>

      <t>Malware frequently uses its own libraries for its activities, and
      those libraries are re-used much like any other software engineering
      project. Research <xref target="malware"></xref> indicates there are
      observable differences in how malware uses encryption compared with
      non-malware uses encryption. There are several interesting findings
      specific to DTLS and TLS which were found common to malware: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Older and weaker cryptographic parameters (e.g.,
          TLS_RSA_WITH_RC4_128_SHA).</t>

          <t>TLS SNI and server certificates are frequently subjects with
          domain generation algorithm (DGA) (e.g., www.33mhwt2j.net).</t>

          <t>Higher use of self-signed certificates compared with typical
          legitimate software.</t>

          <t>Discrepancies in the server name indication (SNI) TLS extension
          in the ClientHello message and the DNS names in the
          SubjectAltName(SAN) X.509 extension in the server certificate
          message.</t>

          <t>Discrepancies in the key exchange algorithm and the client public
          key length in comparison with legitimate flows. As a reminder,
          Client Key Exchange message has been removed from TLS 1.3.</t>

          <t>Lower diversity in TLS client advertised TLS extensions compared
          to legitimate clients.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>If observable (D)TLS profile parameters are used, the following
      discusses the favorable impact on network security:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Although IoT devices that have a single or small number of uses
          might have very broad communication patterns. In such a case, MUD
          rules using ACLs on its own is not suitable for these IoT devices
          but observable (D)TLS profile parameters can be used for such IoT
          devices to permit intended use and to block malicious behaviour of
          IoT devices.</t>

          <t>Several TLS deployments have been vulnerable to active
          Man-In-The-Middle (MITM) attacks because of lack of certificate
          validation. By observing (D)TLS profile parameters, a network
          element can detect when the TLS SNI mismatches the SubjectAltName
          and detect when the server's certificate is invalid, and alert those
          situations.</t>

          <t>IoT device can learn a new skill, and the new skill changes the
          way the IoT device communicates with other devices located in the
          local network and Internet. In other words, if IP addresses and
          domain names the IoT device connects to rapidly changes and MUD
          rules using ACLs cannot be rapidly updated, observable (D)TLS
          profile parameters can be used to permit intended use and to block
          malicious behaviour of IoT device.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This document extends MUD <xref target="RFC8520"></xref> to model
      observable (D)TLS profile parameters. Using these (D)TLS profile
      parameters, an active MUD-enforcing firewall can identify MUD
      non-compliant DTLS and TLS behavior that can indicate malware is running
      on the MUD device. This detection can prevent malware download, block
      access to malicious domains, enforce use of strong ciphers, stop data
      exfiltration, etc. In addition, organizations may have policies around
      acceptable ciphers and certificates on the websites the IoT devices
      connect to. Examples include no use of old and less secure versions of
      TLS, no use of self-signed certificates, deny-list or accept-list of
      Certificate Authorities, valid certificate expiration time, etc. These
      policies can be enforced by observing the (D)TLS profile parameters.
      Enterprise firewall can use the IoT device's (D)TLS profile parameters
      to identify legitimate flows by observation of (D)TLS sessions, and can
      make inferences to permit legitimate flows and to block malicious flows.
      The proposed technique is also suitable in deployments where decryption
      techniques are not ideal due to privacy concerns, non-cooperating
      end-points and expense.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>"(D)TLS" is used for statements that apply to both Transport Layer
      Security <xref target="RFC8446"></xref> and Datagram Transport Layer
      Security <xref target="RFC6347"></xref>. Specific terms are used for any
      statement that applies to either protocol alone.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview of MUD (D)TLS profiles for IoT devices">
      <t>In Enterprise networks, protection and detection are typically done
      both on end hosts and in the network. Host agents have deep visibility
      on the devices where they are installed, whereas the network has broader
      visibility. Installing host agents may not be a viable option on IoT
      devices, and network-based security can only be used to protect such IoT
      devices. (D)TLS profile parameters of IoT device can be used by
      middle-boxes to detect and block malware communication, while at the
      same time preserving the privacy of legitimate uses of encryption.
      Middle-boxes need not proxy (D)TLS but can passively observe the
      parameters of (D)TLS handshakes from IoT devices and gain good
      visibility into TLS 1.0 to 1.2 parameters and partial visibility into
      TLS 1.3 parameters. Malicious agents can try to use the (D)TLS profile
      parameters as legitimate agents to evade detection but it becomes a
      challenge to mimic the behavior of various IoT device types and IoT
      device models from several manufacturers. In other words, malware
      developers will have to develop malicious agents per IoT device type,
      manufacturer and model (which will be several thousands), infect the
      device with specific malware agent and will have keep up with the
      updates to (D)TLS profile parameters of IoT devices. Further, the
      malware command and control server certificates needs to be signed by
      the same certifying authorities trusted by the IoT devices.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="YANG" title="(D)TLS profile YANG module">
      <t>This document specifies a YANG module for representing (D)TLS
      profile. The (D)TLS profile YANG module provides a method for firewall
      to observe the (D)TLS profile parameters in the (D)TLS handshake to
      permit intended use and to block malicious behavior. This module uses
      the common YANG types defined in <xref target="RFC6991"></xref> , rules
      defined in <xref target="RFC8519"></xref> and cryptographic types
      defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-netconf-crypto-types"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The (D)TLS profile parameters include the following:<list
          style="symbols">
          <t>(D)TLS versions supported by the IoT device</t>

          <t>List of supported symmetric encryption algorithms</t>

          <t>List of supported compression methods</t>

          <t>List of extension types</t>

          <t>List of client key exchange algorithms and the client public key
          lengths in versions prior to (D)TLS 1.3</t>

          <t>List of trust anchor certificates used by the IoT device. Note
          that server certificate is encrypted in (D)TLS 1.3 and the
          middle-box without acting as (D)TLS proxy cannot validate the server
          certificate.</t>

          <t>List of DHE or ECDHE groups supported by the client</t>

          <t>List signature algorithms the client can validate in X.509 server
          certificates</t>

          <t>List of SPKI pin sets pre-configured on the client to validate
          self-signed server certificates or raw public keys</t>

          <t>If SNI mismatch is allowed or not, and if SNI mismatch is
          allowed, the server names for which SNI mismatch is allowed. </t>
        </list></t>

      <t>If the (D)TLS profile parameters are not observed in a (D)TLS session
      from the IoT device, the default behaviour is to block the (D)TLS
      session.</t>

      <section title="Tree Structure">
        <t>This document augments the "ietf-mud" MUD YANG module defined in
        <xref target="RFC8520"></xref> for signaling the IoT device (D)TLS
        profile. This document defines the YANG module
        "reddy-opsawg-mud-tls-profile", which has the following tree
        structure:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[module: reddy-opsawg-mud-tls-profile
  augment /mud:mud/mud:from-device-policy:
    +--rw client-profile
       +--rw tls-profiles* [protocol-version supported_versions]
          +--rw protocol-version         uint16
          +--rw supported_versions       boolean
          +--rw encryption-algorithms*   encryption-algorithm
          +--rw compression-methods*     compression-method
          +--rw extension-types*         extension-type
          +--rw acceptlist-ta-certs*     ct:trust-anchor-cert-cms
          +--rw SPKI-pin-sets*           SPKI-pin-set
          +--rw SPKI-hash-algorithm      ct:hash-algorithm-t
          +--rw supported-groups*        supported-group
          +--rw signature-algorithms*    signature-algorithm
          +--rw client-public-keys
          |  +--rw key-exchange-algorithms*     key-exchange-algorithm
          |  +--rw client-public-key-lengths*   client-public-key-length
          +--rw SNI-mismatch-allowed?    boolean
          +--rw server-name*             inet:domain-name
          +--rw actions
             +--rw forwarding    identityref
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="YANG Module">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[module reddy-opsawg-mud-tls-profile {
   yang-version 1.1;
   namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:reddy-opsawg-mud-tls-profile";
   prefix mud-tls-profile;


   import ietf-crypto-types {
     prefix ct;
     reference "draft-ietf-netconf-crypto-types-01: 
                Common YANG Data Types for Cryptography";
   }

   import ietf-inet-types {
     prefix inet;
     reference "Section 4 of RFC 6991";
   }

   import ietf-mud {
     prefix mud;
     reference "RFC 8520";
   }

   import ietf-access-control-list {
     prefix ietf-acl;
     reference
       "RFC 8519: YANG Data Model for Network Access
                  Control Lists (ACLs)";
   }

   organization
     "IETF Operations and Management Area Working Group Working Group";
   contact
      "Editor:  Konda, Tirumaleswar Reddy
               <mailto:TirumaleswarReddy_Konda@McAfee.com>";

   description
     "This module contains YANG definition for configuring
      aliases for resources and filtering rules using DOTS
      data channel.

      Copyright (c) 2019 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
      authors of the code.  All rights reserved.

      Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
      without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject
      to the license terms contained in, the Simplified BSD License
      set forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
      Relating to IETF Documents
      (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).

      This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX; see
      the RFC itself for full legal notices.";

   revision 2019-06-12 {
     description
       "Initial revision.";
   }

   typedef compression-method {
     type uint8;
     description "Compression method.";
   }

   typedef extension-type {
     type uint16;
     description "Extension type.";
   }

   typedef encryption-algorithm {
     type uint16;
     description "Encryption algorithms.";
   }

   typedef supported-group {
     type uint16;
     description "supported DHE or ECDHE group.";
   }

   typedef SPKI-pin-set {
     type binary;
     description "Subject Public Key Info pin set.";
   }

   typedef signature-algorithm {
     type uint16;
     description "Signature algorithm";
   }

   typedef key-exchange-algorithm {
     type uint8;
     description "key exchange algorithm";
   }
   typedef client-public-key-length {
     type uint8;
     description "client public key length";
   }

   augment "/mud:mud/mud:from-device-policy" {
     container client-profile {
       list tls-profiles {
         key "protocol-version supported_versions";
         description
          "(D)TLS version profiles supported by the client";
         leaf protocol-version {
           type uint16;
           description "Legacy protocol version";
         }   
         leaf supported_versions {
           type boolean;
           description "supported versions extension for TLS 1.3";
         }  
         leaf-list encryption-algorithms {
           type encryption-algorithm;   
           description "Encryption algorithms";
         }
         leaf-list compression-methods {
           type compression-method;
            description "Compression methods";
         } 
         leaf-list extension-types {
           type extension-type;
           description "Extension Types";
         }
         leaf-list acceptlist-ta-certs { 
           type ct:trust-anchor-cert-cms;
           description 
             "A list of trust anchor certificates used by the client";
         }
         leaf-list SPKI-pin-sets { 
            type SPKI-pin-set;
            description 
             "A list of SPKI pin sets pre-configured on the client 
              to validate self-signed server certificate or 
              raw public key";
         }
         leaf SPKI-hash-algorithm {
           type ct:hash-algorithm-t;
           description 
             "cryptographic hash algorithm used to generate the SPKI pinset";
         }
         leaf-list supported-groups { 
            type supported-group;
            description 
             "A list of DHE or ECDHE groups supported by the client";
         }
         leaf-list signature-algorithms { 
            type signature-algorithm;
            description 
             "A list signature algorithms the client can validate 
              in X.509 certificates.";
         }
         container client-public-keys {
           when "../supported_versions = 'false'";
           leaf-list key-exchange-algorithms {
             type key-exchange-algorithm; 
             description
             "Key exchange algorithms supported by the client";
           }
           leaf-list client-public-key-lengths {
             type client-public-key-length; 
             description
             "client public key lengths";
           }
         }  
         leaf SNI-mismatch-allowed {
           type boolean;
           default "false";
           description
            "If set to 'false', SNI mismatch is not allowed.";
         } 
         leaf-list server-name {
            when "../SNI-mismatch-allowed = 'true'";
            type inet:domain-name;
            description
            "Server names (FQDN) for which SNI mismatch is allowed.";
         }
         container actions {
           description
           "Definitions of action for this profile.";
           leaf forwarding {
             type identityref {
               base ietf-acl:forwarding-action;
             }
             mandatory true;
             description
             "Specifies the forwarding action for the (D)TLS profile.";
             reference
             "RFC 8519: YANG Data Model for Network Access
                           Control Lists (ACLs)";
           }  
         }
       }
     }
   }
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="(D)TLS 1.3 handshake">
      <t>In (D)TLS 1.3, full (D)TLS handshake inspection is not possible since
      all (D)TLS handshake messages excluding the ClientHello message are
      encrypted. (D)TLS 1.3 has introduced new extensions in the handshake
      record layers called Encrypted Extensions. Using these extensions
      handshake messages will be encrypted and network devices (such as a
      firewall) are incapable deciphering the handshake, thus cannot view the
      server certificate. However, a few parameters in the ServerHello are
      still visible such as the chosen cipher. Note that Client Key Exchange
      message has been removed from (D)TLS 1.3.</t>

      <section title="Encrypted SNI">
        <t>To increase privacy, encrypted SNI <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-tls-sni-encryption"></xref> prevents passive
        observation of the TLS Server Name Indication and to effectively
        provide privacy protection, SNI encryption needs to be used in
        conjunction with DNS encryption (e.g., DNS-over-(D)TLS or DNS-
        over-HTTPS). Firewall inspecting the (D)TLS 1.3 handshake cannot
        decrypt encrypted SNI. If an IoT device is configured to use public
        DNS servers the policy enforcement point is moved to that public
        server, which cannot enforce the MUD policy based on domain names
        (Section 8 of <xref target="RFC8520"></xref>). Thus the use of a
        public DNS server is incompatible with MUD. A local DNS server is
        necessary to allow MUD policy enforcement on the local network <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-doh-resolver-associated-doh"></xref> and <xref
        target="I-D.reddy-dprive-bootstrap-dns-server"></xref>. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Full (D)TLS 1.3 handshake inspection">
        <t>Middle-box needs to act as a (D)TLS 1.3 proxy to observe the
        parameters of (D)TLS handshakes from IoT devices and gain good
        visibility into TLS 1.3 parameters. The following steps explain the
        mechanism to automatically bootstrap IoT devices with local network's
        CA certificates and to enable the middle-box to act as a (D)TLS 1.3
        proxy.<list style="symbols">
            <t>Bootstrapping Remote Secure Key Infrastructures (BRSKI)
            discussed in <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra"></xref> provides a
            solution for secure automated bootstrap of devices. BRSKI
            specifies means to provision credentials on devices to be used to
            operationally access networks. In addition, BRSKI provides an
            automated mechanism for the bootstrap distribution of CA
            certificates from the Enrollment over Secure Transport (EST) <xref
            target="RFC7030"></xref> server. The IoT device can use BRSKI to
            automatically bootstrap the IoT device using the IoT manufacturer
            provisioned X.509 certificate, in combination with a registrar
            provided by the local network and IoT device manufacturer's
            authorizing service (MASA). <list style="numbers">
                <t>The IoT device authenticates to the local network using the
                IoT manufacturer provisioned X.509 certificate. The IoT device
                can request and get a voucher from the MASA service via the
                registrar. The voucher is signed by the MASA service and
                includes the local network's CA public key.</t>

                <t>The IoT device validates the signed voucher using the
                manufacturer installed trust anchor associated with the MASA,
                stores the CA's public key and validates the provisional TLS
                connection to the registrar.</t>

                <t>The IoT device requests the full EST distribution of
                current CA certificates (Section 5.9.1 in <xref
                target="I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra"></xref>) from
                the registrar operating as a BRSKI-EST server. The IoT device
                stores the CA certificates as Explicit Trust Anchor database
                entries. The IoT device uses the Explicit Trust Anchor
                database to validate the server certificate.</t>

                <t>The middle-box uses the "supported_versions" TLS extension
                (defined in TLS 1.3 to negotiate the supported TLS versions
                between client and server) to determine the TLS version.
                During the (D)TLS handshake, If (D)TLS version 1.3 is used,
                the middle-box ((D)TLS proxy) modifies the certificate
                provided by the server and signs it with the private key from
                the local CA certificate. The middle-box has visibility into
                further exchanges between the IoT device and server which
                enables it to inspect the (D)TLS 1.3 handshake, enforce the
                MUD (D)TLS profile and can inspect subsequent network
                traffic.</t>

                <t>The IoT device uses the Explicit Trust Anchor database to
                validate the server certificate.</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The proposed technique empowers the middle-box to reject (D)TLS 1.3
        sessions that violate the MUD (D)TLS profile. </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Example" title="MUD File Example">
      <t>This example below contains (D)TLS profile parameters for a IoT
      device. JSON encoding of YANG modelled data <xref
      target="RFC7951"></xref> is used to illustrate the example.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[{
   "ietf-mud:mud": {
     "mud-version": 1,
      "mud-url": "https://example.com/IoTDevice",
      "last-update": "2019-18-06T03:56:40.105+10:00",
      "cache-validity": 100,
      "is-supported": true,
      "systeminfo": "IoT device name",
      "reddy-opsawg-mud-tls-profile:from-device-policy": {
        "client-profile": {
          "tls-version-profile" : [
           {
                 "protocol-version" : 0x0303,
                 "supported_versions_ext" : FALSE,
                 "encryption-algorithms" : [31354, 4865, 4866, 4867],  
                 "extension-types" : [10],  
                 "supported-groups" : [29],  
                 "actions": {
                   "forwarding": "accept"
                 }
           }
          ]  
        }

      }
    }
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations in <xref target="RFC8520"></xref> need to be
      taken into consideration.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document requests IANA to register the following URIs in the
      "ns" subregistry within the "IETF XML Registry" <xref
      target="RFC3688"></xref>: <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[      URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:reddy-opsawg-mud-tls-profile
      Registrant Contact: The IESG.
      XML: N/A; the requested URI is an XML namespace.
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>TODO</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6991"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8446"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6347"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8519"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3688'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tls-dtls13" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-netconf-crypto-types" ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8520'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8445'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7478'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7951'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7030"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tls-sni-encryption" 
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-doh-resolver-associated-doh'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.reddy-dprive-bootstrap-dns-server'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra'?>

      <reference anchor="malware" target="https://arxiv.org/abs/1607.01639">
        <front>
          <title>Deciphering Malware&rsquo;s use of TLS (without
          Decryption)</title>

          <author fullname="Blake Anderson" initials="B." surname="Anderson">
            <organization>Cisco</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Subharthi Paul" initials="S." surname="Paul">
            <organization>Cisco</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="David McGrew" initials="D." surname="McGrew">
            <organization>Cisco</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2016" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
